<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article>
  <title>RAGE::SDL : The C++ wrapper for SDL</title>

  <section>
    <title>Features</title>

    <para>This library is mostly a C++ portable layer over the <ulink
    url="http://www.libsdl.org">Smart DirectMedia Library</ulink>. The aim is
    to have a C++ interface to SDL. Users should be able to use it simply and
    have at least a "default consistent behaviour".</para>

    <para>AS soon as the wrapping of SDL is complete, we will start looking at
    wrapping all the SDL "Standard Libs" in the same way.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Graphic Interface</title>

      <para>The graphic interface is a pure virtual class called "Engine". you
      need to derivate it with you own if you want to be able to display
      something in your SDL window. You can use either OpenGL functions or
      RAGE::SDL 2D functions, providing you created the Window with the
      correct settings.</para>

      <para>If you are using 2D functions you might want to the Video
      Interface inside the Engine.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Input Interface</title>

      <para>The input interface is made by EventManager, Joystick, Keyboard,
      Mouse. You will probably need to extend them to implement the behaviour
      you want.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Audio Interface</title>

      <para>None yet.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Video Interface</title>

      <para>The video Interface is made by RGBSurface, VideoSurface and
      GLSurface mostly.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>OS Functions</title>

      <para>None yet</para>

      <section>
        <title>Timer</title>

        <para>None yet</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Threads</title>

        <para>None yet</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>RWOps</title>

        <para>None yet</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Common Core Components</title>

      <para>This is a list of usefull features added only for the need of this
      C++ wrapper. But still they might be usefull somewhere else, and are not
      really related to the main subject fo the C++ wrapper</para>

      <section>
        <title>Logger</title>

        <para>The Logger class is the only feature that was needed so
        far.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Dependencies</title>

    <para>- <ulink url="http://www.libsdl.org">SDL</ulink>
    <emphasis>mandatory.</emphasis></para>

    <para>To come :</para>

    <para>- SDL_image</para>

    <para>- SDL_mixer</para>

    <para>- SDL_net</para>

    <para>- SDL_ttf</para>

    <para>- SDL_rtf</para>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>How to build, test and install</title>

    <para></para>

    <section>
      <title>Code::Blocks build</title>

      <para>I am personnaly using CodeBlocks on windows with mingw to build
      RAGE::SDL. However it misses a dependency checking for the libraries
      needed. At the moment it is not a big problem as only SDL is needed. But
      while we will add more dependencies CMake will be used to have a
      consistent way of building RAGE::SDL.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>CMake build</title>

      <para>If you want to be able to build RAGE::SDL using your own favorite
      environment, try the CMake build. It generates files for most of the
      compilers / build system.</para>

      <para>The good thing with CMake is that it will check the dependencies
      available on your system and help you to configure your system for
      development.</para>

      <para></para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Setting up the build environment to work
      with CMake :</emphasis></para>

      <para>- <emphasis role="bold">Windows</emphasis> : I advise MS Visual
      Express 8 2005, as it is free, just need to register. You will need to
      install the platform SDK and make sure the directories are correctly
      setup, cf. Microsoft Website</para>

      <para>If something goes wrong (cmake doesnt detect your cl.exe properly)
      try <literal>cmake --debug-trycompile</literal> it will output a
      VSProject that you can try to open and build with VStudio, and find out
      what happens...</para>

      <para>temporary note : with cmake 2.2.3, you might need to install SQL
      to have the minimum required library to build the test project. This
      should be fixed in 2.2.4.</para>

      <para>- <emphasis role="bold">Unix/Linux</emphasis> : just need to have
      GNUmake installed which is pretty standard (or really easy to get) on
      every Unix/Linux I am aware of ^^.</para>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Testing RAGE::SDL</title>

      <para>There are a few test that are usefull to test the C++ wrapper.
      most of them are still the old SDL tests, not yet using the wrapper...
      lots of work to do.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Installing RAGE::SDL</title>

      <para>RAGE::SDL will be built as a dynamic library or a static library.
      Right now only the static library is built</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Using RAGE::SDL</title>

      <para>The online generated doc is available <ulink
      url="doxygen/html">here</ulink>, thanks to <ulink
      url="http://www.doxygen.org">Doxygen</ulink>.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Source overview : UML Diagrams</title>

    <para></para>

    <section>
      <title>Overview</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Detailed</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>